A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Project Specialist in Communications, Office Files of William O. Sweeney FA571
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Project Specialist in Communications, Office Files of William O. Sweeney
1968-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sweeney, William O., 1931-
Ford Foundation
FA571
1.6 Cubic Feet 4 Hollinger document boxes
The Office Files of William O. Sweeney document his work as a project specialist in population communications for the Foundation from 1969 to 1981. The collection is organized into two series: Project Files (1970-1980), and Reports and Writings (1968-1977). Mr. Sweeney's Project Files detail his work on the Foundation's Population Communications Project. The Reports and Writings focus on population communications. The files hold research reports, evaluations, conference papers and other writings authored by Mr. Sweeney The earliest Foundation grants for population research and family planning occurred under the aegis of the Divisions of International Affairs or Overseas Development. The Population Program was officially established in 1963, and became part of the International Division in 1966. Following a Foundation-wide reorganization in 1981, the Population program became an independent program area. In 1992 the Population Program was subsumed into Reproductive Health and Population. Following the Foundation-wide reorganization in 1997, Reproductive Health and Population became Human Development and Reproductive Health, a subset of the ASSETS Program. William O. Sweeney was retained by the Foundation as Project Specialist for the Population Communications Project when that project was initiated in 1969. Throughout his time with Ford, he travelled extensively assisting developing nations such as China, Egypt, Indonesia, Kenya, Korea, the Philippines, Thailand and Vietnam with the establishment of family planning programs.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Biographical / Historical
The earliest Foundation grants for population research and family planning occurred under the aegis of the Divisions of International Affairs or Overseas Development. The Population Program was officially established in 1963, and became part of the International Division in 1966. Following a Foundation-wide reorganization in 1981, the Population program once again was made independent. In 1992 the Population Program was subsumed into Reproductive Health and Population. Following a second Foundation-wide reorganization in 1997, Reproductive Health and Population became Human Development and Reproductive Health, a subset of the ASSETS Program.
Biographical / Historical
William O. Sweeney received a J.D. from University of Pennsylvania. Before he joined the Foundation, he worked for Newsweek magazine and the Cursillo Movement of the Roman Catholic Church. The Foundation retained Mr. Sweeney as Project Specialist its Population Communications Project in 1969. Throughout his time with Ford, he helped developing nations to establish family planning programs.
He left the Foundation in 1981. Subsequently Mr. Sweeney was Executive Director of the International Institute of Communications in London and later the International Advertising Association in New York. He died on July 4, 1987 at age 55.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of William O. Sweeney document his work as a project specialist for the Foundation over a span of twenty years. His records document his work in population communications as an advisor to governments in China, Egypt, Indonesia, Kenya, Korea, the Philippines, Thailand, Vietnam and elsewhere. Available in this collection are research reports that Mr. Sweeney prepared throughout his tenure at the Foundation.
One project file of note concerns the proposed establishment of Cycle Communications Associates (CCA), a non-profit agency (1978-1980). Its purpose was to advise non-profits and governments about population communications. Because of concerns that it was not needed, CCA did not receive sustaining Foundation support.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in two series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Project Files, 1970-1980
Series II. Reports and Writings, 1968-1977
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
- Project Files, 1970-1980; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the files Mr. Sweeney kept of his work on the Foundation's Population Communications Project and Cycle Communications Associates. The files contain proposals, research, memoranda and correspondence.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - China -- Memoranda Re: UNFPA Communications and Family Planning Project, Project Agreement, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Incorporation of CCA, Research on Incorporation Process, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Memoranda Re: Closing Out DAP in Population and Proposal for Establishing CCA, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cycle Communications Associates (CCA) -- Proposal to Establish CCA, 1980 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DAP Grant Recommendations to Extend Consultancy in Family Planning and Population Communications, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - East-West Communication Institute International Conference on Making Population/Family Planning Research Useful, Honolulu, HI -- Agenda, Discussion Summaries, Papers, 1973 December 3-7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Egypt -- Memoranda Re: UNFPA and AID-Sponsored Family Planning Missions, Assessment of AID/Cairo Project, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Population Communications Project -- Evaluation Outline and Comments on Report, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation Population Communications Project -- Evaluation Report, 1980 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Indonesia -- Memoranda Re: Ford Jakarta Field Office Support for National Family Planning Education, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (1 of 3), 1970 June 6-18 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (2 of 3), 1970 June 6-18 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Workshop on Communications in Family Planning Programs, Tehran, Iran -- Preliminary Report to the Ford Foundation (3 of 3), 1970 June 6-18 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kenya -- Consulting Report on Developing a Family Planning Communications Plan, Proposal to Train Population Communications Personnel, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Korea -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Background on Planned Parenthood Federation of Korea Mothers' Clubs, etc., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda -- From Sweeney to Population Office Colleagues Re: Journey from Dacca, Bangladesh to Lomé, Togo, 1977 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Philippines -- Correspondence Re: Workshop to Draft Communications Strategy for Philippine Population Program, 1978 June 20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Resources on Development -- Reports, Papers on U.S. Private Voluntary Organizations (PVOs) and Development Education, Videotape as a Development Tool, etc., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resources on Population Communications -- Papers on Computer and Videotape Communications Technology, Population Education in Developing Countries (1 of 2), 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Resources on Population Communications -- Papers on Computer and Videotape Communications Technology, Population Education in Developing Countries (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Consulting Work with UNFPA and DTCP (Development Training and Communication Planning) (1 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Consulting Work with UNFPA and DTCP, Report, Terms of Agreement (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thailand -- Memoranda Re: Orientation Program for Indochinese Refugees, Background, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - USAID -- Memoranda Re: Grants to Private Voluntary Organizations and Matching Grants Policy, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam -- Memoranda Re: Meeting with Audiovisual Center for Family Planning, 1980 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reports and Writings, 1968-1977; II
  This series holds Mr. Sweeney's reports and writings on the subject of population communications. It includes two foreign language reports, one concerning Costa Rica (Spanish language) and the about North Africa (French language).
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Predictions of Attitude Change for U.S. Roman Catholics", 1968 August 19 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Family Planning Communications in Nigeria" (consulting report), 1969 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Suggestions for an Education and Public Information Program for Nutrition, Maternal and Child Health, and Population in Costa Rica" (consulting report), 1969 September (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "El Salvador: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", 1970 May (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Guatemala: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", 1970 June (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Kenya: Developing a Family Planning Communications Plan for 1970-1971" (consulting report), 1970 August (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Central America and Some Caribbean Countries: A Report on Population and Family Planning Information, Education and Communications Programs", 1970 November (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Jamaica: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning", 1970 November (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Ghana: Family Planning Communications: A Program Status Report", 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Planning Suggestions for Communications Programs", 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Role of Communications in Family Planning and Population Programs," 1st International Planned Parenthood Federation Workshop on Information and Education, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 1971 November 27-December 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "A Blueprint for Program Planning for Population Communication," Work-Planning Conference, University of Chicago Community and Family Study Center, 1971 December 16-17 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Communications Program Planning Needs Which Can Be Fulfilled by Library and Information Services," 5th National Conference on Population/Family Planning Library and Information Services, Chapel Hill, NC, 1972 May (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The Role of Communications in Population and Family Planning Programs", 1972 May (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Population and Family Planning: An Approach to Communications as a Program Component", 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Using Commercial Resources in Population Communications Programs", 1972 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Papel Que Desempeñan las Comunicaciones en los Programas de Población y Planificación Familiar," Universidad de Costa Rica Centro de Estudios Sociales y de Población, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "A Report on a Visit to Nigeria to Consult on Communications Activities of the Family Planning Council of Nigeria", 1973 March (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Communications and the Population Program of Pakistan", 1973 August (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Communications and Population in the Philippines: Report of a Visit", 1973 September (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Evaluation of the East-West Communications Institute", 1973 September (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "A Communication en Afrique," Seminaire sur les Problemes de Population et les Mass Media en Afrique du Nord et au Moyen-Orient, Tunis, Tunisia, 1973 September 24-29 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Methodology to Support Research Utilization Practitioners," Conference on Making Population/Family Planning Research Useful, East-West Center, Honolulu, HI, 1973 December 3-7 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Audiencias para Programas de Información y Educación en Planificación Familiar," Asociación Demográfica Costarricense, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Population Communications in the Philippines: Report of a Consultant Visit", 1974 July (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "The Scope of Communications in the Development of Human Resources in the Less Industrialized Countries," Teachers College Record, 1974 December (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Exchange of Information Between Nations: Help in Solving Population Problems," Bulletin of the American Society for Information Science Vol. 1, No. 8, 1975 March (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Population/Family Planning Media Communications in 25 Countries" (monograph), 1977 June (Box 4, Folder 14)